I was a little terrified backstage when
Palmer's like, "There's something on the
screen that says I'm not supposed to say
this." I was like, "For the love of God,
whatever it is, please not be please
don't make it about colossal.
>> Please don't say it."
Uh, so I remember at uh at Abundance 360
last March um just before you came on,
Elon was there. Uh and you you said uh
yeah, I want a pet woolly mammoth. How
you doing on that project?
>> Uh we get that request. Yeah. Yeah. But
but there was actually an amazing uh I
think it was either American Dad or
Family Guy episode where they explained
Did you see this? I don't know if you
guys saw this, but there's like flame
crisper and it was amazing. And it was
amazing cuz then at the end they're
like, "Yeah, and the woolly mammoths
came out and they're about the size of a
dog. That's actually how big they were.
The fossils were just wrong, right?" So,
[laughter]
uh, it was like amazing cuz it explains
Christopher, but I was like, you know,
uh, we get the request like the number
two request we get is teacup mammoths.
>> Teacup.
>> Teacup mammoth. Like,
>> yeah, everybody wants a teacup. Like
they want to they want to take a mammoth
and put it like Yeah. Put it and put it
in your purse, right? And so when I mean
we can engineer a new melanin and make
it pink and then Paris may want
[laughter] it. So we're uh uh we are not
working on that currently. Um but we're
making good progress on the Mammoth
project. So
>> amazing. Uh so let me kick this off. So
you've started like four successful
companies before Colossal and in gaming
in defense in AI in mobile and so you
knew nothing about synthetic biology. I
yeah before before you started now a
company worth over10 billion dollars.
>> So why what made you make the extinction
your moonshot
>> and having no background in synthetic
biology? Was that a hindrance or an
advantage?
>> Oh, I think it's a massive uh advantage.
Um you know I I think that it affords me
the opportunity to go into rooms of you
know Palmer talked a little bit about
this too of like hiring people to
replace you and hiring people that are
much smarter than you, right? And so I
get, what's great about this from my
vantage point is like I get to deal with
a lot of the same but at the
same time I can go in and like sit down
with like best Shapiro and learn about
ancient DNA extraction and like how not
to do things, but then at the same but
then like the next meeting I can go
learn about like where we're pushing the
boundaries of multiplex editing and how
many edits that we can make at once,
right? So, I would say that um you know
I I knew how to and I guess in all of my
career I've known how to ask the right
questions because I'm really curious.
But um I really do kind of subscribe to
that old adage of like putting the top
smartest women and men around you just
asking them the questions, right? And so
I get to go to meetings to just ask
questions. And you know 90% of the time
I think people are like okay if you knew
more about biology this meeting would go
faster. But then 10% of the time but
then 10% of the time they're like we
never thought of it that way. Right? is
>> by the way this is such an important uh
lesson for all of us as entrepreneurs
right just because you're not an expert
in an area doesn't make it an area that
you shouldn't go into if you love if
you're attract the best talent around
you
>> yeah George Church and like this is the
only brag that I will say which I'm very
proud of George Church says that I am
the best student he's never had because
I will literally just pepper him and be
like hey my favorite times of the year
are during holiday seasons when like no
one's working because I will just get on
calls for hours and hours and hours with
George Church and just talk about the
possibilities with synthetic biology.
>> Who's George Church for a bit?
>> So, so if you don't know George, George
is the father of arguably the father of
synthetic biology. He's the head of
genetics at Harvard and um you know he's
a lot of the nextgen readr technologies
that were invented came out of the
church lab and his lab's prolific. It's
there's been numerous multi-billion
dollar companies that have spun out of
the lab. is probably the probably most
active startup biology lab in the world
and and he's also he's also like 67 with
like narcolepsy and hilarious
>> and such a sweetheart guy.
>> Yeah. And I mean he is the most
collaborative person ever, right? And so
he's he's also like hardcore even though
it doesn't come from software he's
hardcore into open source and just like
trying the democratization of
technologies like genome sequencing. he
wanted that to go from billions to $100,
which he was very active in that
category. And so, um, he is literally
just the most collaborative co-founder
I've ever, you know, had the pleasure of
working with.
>> Dave, yeah, I'm really curious about the
business model of biology. And this is
like I think we all know that of all the
use cases of AI that are imminent, like
solving all disease, curing all pain is
just like highest on the priority list.
Uh, the business model in biology is
just always
>> Yeah. So I mean and it's great to get
your perspective as a serial
entrepreneur who came into biology from
the outside. So so my first question on
like the business model is uh the
foundation models like we just saw that
like out of the box Astra can drive a
car.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Is it going to do biology
out of the box or do you say no no no no
no no no we need to build our own have
to so the foundation models now and
we've been very fortunate to work with
both open AAI and um anthropic on and
getting early access to some of that
stuff which has been great for a long
time we were leveraging it for kind of
like thoughtful middleware right coming
from a software perspective where we
were connecting lab notebooks and Jira I
mean one of the hardest things that we
did at the company was uh retrain
scientists to work in Jira
So that's harder than stem cell re
programming at times. And so uh and so
we we actually for a long time, you
know, these the LLMs before the frontier
models, uh were really good at writing
term papers, right? But they weren't
really great at doing like ancestral
state reconstruction or comparative
genomics, right? Like that that's where
they just didn't work, which would have
been amazing. So for a long time, we
were leveraging them for kind of like
middleware layers of infrastructure. So
you don't have to go hire the deoits or
accenturers of the world to build all
these systems and reporting. Right? So
we did a I think we were very successful
at deploying that for a long long time.
Now they're getting pretty far where you
can run simulation uh experiments. Uh
there's a bunch of companies out there
that are standing up Laya and others
that are like trying to do lab
automation around it. Right? We've been
pretty thoughtful about how and when we
invest in that category. But I think
that what you're going to find is you're
going to find interesting insights
between connections that are really
still language problems, right? So like,
so for example, if you go search the
literature on, you know, everything on
mice, you know, if you just want to go
build a a new therapy company or or
whatever for humans and you go look at
all of the published papers on mice,
many of them uh they'll call a gene a
different thing. They'll classify it
differently, they'll run that experiment
slightly differently. And so so
[clears throat] you know if you if you
go try to run the exact same experiment
you're going to get like somewhere
between 40 and 60% failure rate on
published work which is terrible right
so where I think AI is going to be
really helpful in the next kind of wave
of uh outside of like small molecule
drug discovery I think it'll be very
very helpful uh kind of eliminating that
gap and bridging kind of that
nomenclature between work like there'll
be times where we'll do work and we'll
find out later that there was a
peer-reviewed published paper on on one
of the things that we trying to solve,
but the way we were looking for it
wasn't findable um on PubMot. So, so I
think in the short term it's going to
bridge the communication layer, but I do
think you're going to, and you saw this,
I think Anthropic announced this a
couple days ago, right, where they've um
and you have Genko and others that are
now going to test it. You're still going
to need to have a wet lab experiment to
test and validate those. But running
simulation uh design across a myriad of
different experiments and helping
creatively come up with the next
experiment. I think that's where we're
going to see AI and biology for the
next, you know, 3 to 5 years. But what
about this like like if if I think about
text data and research results and going
through, you know, thousands and
thousands of prior tests, that's all LLM
city.
>> But what if my input vector is just a
gene sequence? Like if I dump that right
now into Anthropic, pretty sure nothing
good is going to come out the other.
>> Yeah. But but at scale. So, so thank you
for the tea up. Um so that is what that
that is what I fundamentally believe is
the importance of our global bio system
that we're rolling out. Right. So we're
trying to roll out this like Noah's Arc
2.0 model. Uh not that Noah didn't get
it really right in the first stage, but
um like at least our ours is slightly
different. We're doing like a tax
sequencing and other things that he
didn't do. Um, and so we're going out
and and trying to work with governments
around the world to stand up localized
bios to get all of that so that we can
do TTOT sequencing. And so to your
point, I do not think that a single
genome is going to uh like you're not
going to feed it into mythos and it's
going to be like, oh, if you make these
six changes, it's immortal, right? But I
think that if you go look at like you
know uh uh you know thousands of genomes
across uh all these evolutionary uh
lanes in in aven species and see that
they are not susceptible to many of
these diseases. You'll look at that
right we're doing that on a small scale
um with uh things like p-53 immortal
jellyfishes other things looking at at
kind of like known outcomes of the
species and then try to backtrack it
down the tree of life. We're we're doing
some of that right now at one of our
companies which we're pretty excited
about and early indications are
positive. Um but but to your point,
you're not just going to be able throw a
genome in and it's going to be like oh
here's how you fix it and makes it
perfect. But I do think that that amount
of data from a comparative genomics
perspective at scale is will get you
there.
>> But I also think that um so so I would
make the argument that you know the data
set the is more valuable than the model.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Because I have the data set.
>> We've made that point so [laughter] many
times. Alex. Huh.
>> Yeah. I'd love to talk a bit about
deextinction. I'm cognizant that you now
have four plus spin-offs and but
nonetheless deextinction I think is
still what you and Colossal are perhaps
best
>> and certain things we're not supposed to
talk about.
>> We won't talk about those though.
So the extinction there was a a Russian
philosopher Nikolai Fodorov late 19th
century parent of a strain of philosophy
called Russian cosmism that argued that
the ultimate trajectory of humanity in
developing science and technology would
be essentially to develop the technology
to revive every human who's ever lived.
Russian cosmism you can look it up. So
deextinction in in some sense you are
>> we are not doing that currently.
>> Uh [laughter]
good to know.
>> So in but in some sense by uh
deexttinguishing deextincting various
model species including the woolly
mammoth you're the first company to my
knowledge on earth that at least has a
plausible business model or at least
technical trajectory to try to go after
the entire historical biosphere. So
maybe not even just every human who's
ever lived, but every nonhuman organism
that's ever lived.
>> Right?
>> In an era of super intelligence where
grand challenges are falling left and
right, do you think that humanity's
common task as the 19th century Russian
cosmists thought that we'll ultimately
have the technology to revive every
organism that's ever lived or at least
every human? Do you foresee that
becoming possible?
>> I do not. I think through syn through
DNA synthesis prediction models and uh
you know some level some components of
synthetic biology we will be able to get
pretty close approximates. I don't think
though with two big caveats. Number one
just like I have those other colossal
does not use any of our technologies at
Colossal for humans. So we won't do that
even though I think our
>> You don't need a spin-off for that. Is
that what you're saying? I think that
that when you start working with humans,
you need different uh sometimes
different investors sometime and
definitely different governance, right?
And you go through a different process
>> and more patience
>> and and more patience, right? That was
actually really good advice I got from
Bob Nelson. Bob Nelson in the early days
was like, hey, don't apply any of this
to humans for a while because you
effectively go into like code freeze
with the FDA and it's just a like you're
just going to be in this monotony
forever. go sol go get to the
technologies until they plateau before
you then take them out. But but back to
your question, I think that
fundamentally um most organisms remember
these are the most organisms that we
know. Very few people re uh realize
this, but there's like less than like a
hundred T-Rexes that have ever been I
just I just want to go down the path
that will scare you. There's there's uh
less than like a hundred T-Rexes that
have ever been been found, right? But
with that, you know, there's billions
that allegedly were on Earth at at at
different points in time, right? And so
very few things uh leave a fossil
record. So I think it's more likely that
we will be able to engineer life from a
programmable life perspective in the way
that we want it than just bring back
everything that ever existed because I
don't even think we know, right? I think
is probably highly likely based on uh AI
super intelligence at some point where
we get to the point where we're saying
oh we're going to engineer this thing
and to to your question uh maybe it did
exist but we just never know because it
left no fossil records right so I think
it's more likely that we will be
engineering life to our advantage and
trying to bring back things and even if
colossal or a subset of our technologies
both cloning and and genome engineering
can bring back things as you know
environmental factors epigenetics all
these other things like if we could
clone Mozart, that doesn't mean that
he's going to come out and be like, "Oh,
I'm I'm I'm going to like solve where
where the terrible trajectory of music
has gone."
>> Well, just maybe a follow-up question.
So, for for Mozart specifically, we do
know quite a bit about Mozart's life.
So, our argu if we did want to resurrect
Mozart, we'd have no problem at all with
reconstructing his childhood
environment.
>> I to to to a point, right? Like like to
a point, right? And so I'm not in and by
the way, just to be very clear, I am not
encouraging in any way this line of
questioning, but we are taking humans
and growing them. I was like, you're
going to make like that you're going to
go down this like Michael Jordan LeBron
super basketball team in a second and
scare me. So um the uh I do think it's
highly likely that that if we were able
or it's not highly it's 100% accurate to
say that we understand their genetic
disposition and aptitude towards these
certain uh traits and under the right uh
environments. If you want to go like you
know um if if if you want to go all
simulation design on them and put them
in the right environments then they
could probably then then your Mozart 2.0
could probably be better than the mo
most.
>> But but Ben, let's bring it back to the
animal kingdom because right now the
whole thesis is that the AI systems can
design the genome sequence that reflect
a phenotype. So if you want an animal
that's not 100% there yet, but
>> but it's that's that's the objective,
right? If you want animal that's got a
longer snout or an animal that has
wings. So, like I asked you on stage at
FII, you know, could you make a Pikachu?
>> Yeah, that that seems to be a weird like
fan favorite. You know, people are more
accepting, I think, of Pikachu than um
these large genetic human camps that
that you're thinking
>> branded species.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yes. Yeah. I think people
are more uh open to that model of of of
genome engineering than
>> But it's it sounds just maybe to tie a
bow on this, it sounds like it isn't a
technical objection per se. It's it's
more worries of social, political,
regulatory concern.
>> That's correct. Yes. And ethical.
>> So this is where this is where I'd like
to jump in. You know, in Stuart Brand
made this famous comment, Peter named
the title of your book. He said, "We are
as gods. We might as well start acting
like them, right?" And he said that in
1968. Um we are at a point where you can
deextinct or bring back any species. How
do you g think through the ethics of
what should we bring back? Which ones?
Which ones shouldn't we bring back?
>> I'm a huge Stewart fan. You know, I love
him. Love Ryan. That quote has been out
there kind of like, you know, uh, Minnie
from a a famous dinosaur movie. Um, but,
uh, I don't know if I would characterize
it like Steuart would then get like on a
plane. But, um, but from my perspective,
um, I would say that like we spend a lot
of time. It is not plausible yet to
bring back everything or engineer
everything from a synthetic biology
perspective. So we try to be very
thoughtful and people ask us is there a
checklist? How exactly do you go about
selecting your species? Uh because
there's a species that we've been very
public about and then there species that
we have not hold on. I'm not think I'm
not talking about what you're doing
specifically.
>> Oh, you're saying philosophy?
>> Generally philosophically, right? If we
could bring back any species, who gets
to decide? What evidence do you use to
say oh bring this back or that? just
from a societal ethics perspective, how
should we be
>> speciesism, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And so it it's a great question
and because we're kind of the um you
know guinea pig in this world. Uh the
way that we think about it is what was
their contribution to the environment?
What was their contribution uh to the
food web? What was their why did they go
extinct? Uh what how do indigenous
people feel about it? Right? Like some
of the species that we work on,
>> they have a deep spiritual connection to
the indigenous uh people side of it.
Right? Right? So, I don't think you're
going to walk in and quote Steuart Brand
to him, right? And so, I think that it's
very important to kind of like factor
all those and weight those and we're
probably going to get it wrong and I
think societyy's going to get it wrong,
but we're going to continue to try. But
then we also look at like is there an
educational benefit to it, right? Like
one of the things that we did when we
did the direwolves, right, after working
with the indigenous people groups and uh
the redwolf coalition teams and all
these different components is we did we
did weigh in the pop culture nature to
it. We thought, is there a way that we
can bring all these people that focus on
um sci-fi in Game of Thrones and Magic
the Gathering? Can we bring them to Wolf
Conservation and can we bring them can
we teach them about genome engineering
because we put we we brought something
back that they thought was only a
mythological creature in their fantasy
universe. Right? So, so we we try to
weight all of these things differently.
um there's not a perfect kind of
internal algorithm for how we look at
it. But I do think that as the
technologies proliferate and more
governments start deploying our
technologies, they will have to wait
that on an individual basis.
>> They will.
>> So Ben,
>> and I'm sure that all of us are going to
get it wrong at some point.
>> Well, because it's there's so many
different factors involved, right? Like
I'm some uh indigenous tribe and I
worship the Tasmanian devil. That
doesn't mean you should or shouldn't
bring it back. There's all sorts of
other factors. We're gonna have to think
through that at a very because the power
that you're bringing to the table here
is something that we've never seen in
the history of humanity.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I mean it is it is
>> you're like you're like a walking
singularity.
>> Yeah. We are um
>> we we do uh I I think that society
doesn't fully understand. I mean they
also address Jurassic Park and I think
that they've all heard like Ian Malcolm
like talk about it but I do think he was
really right. Like I do think that the
technologies that are being developed
with the kind of intersection of
synthetic biology, compute, AI, and then
eventually quantum will be more powerful
than any weapon system that's ever been
created by far.
>> Ben, we talk about solving everything.
We talk about, you know, math is cooked,
physics is next, chemistry and biology.
Is there an inflection point, a
singularity in biology where all of a
sudden there's a complete knowledge base
of all the ingested DNA, all the all the
ingested phenotypes, and you can
literally design an or software for
biology.
>> You can design you could you could
prompt,
>> give me an animal that does this.
>> Yeah, I think that DNA synthesis isn't
quite there yet.
>> But project for me here.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So So I think that world is
less than 10 years out.
>> Okay. All right. So you can prompt your
favorite Pikachu or animal within 10
years.
>> Whoever owns those technologies should
do it for you. But I do think that the
technologies of being able to engineer
key phenotypes on base level organisms
in different clays and be able to uh
synthesize them or multiplex engineer
them and then grow them exudo is within
a decade.
>> Okay. Exuter within.
>> Talk about talk about your your what's
that?
>> Within a decade.
>> Holy This is unbelievable.
>> Well, well, let me let me give you a
current curve and this doesn't obviously
mean that it's going to continue on this
curve, but you know, we were taking
victory laps at 20 edits deliver and I
think that 99% of biioarma and uh I'd
say 99% of biioarma and academia would
do that today. Um we are delivering 300
plus at 90 plus% efficiency
consistently. Right. That was that was a
year ago.
>> Wow.
>> Right. We're now testing thousand uh
>> so that's an exponential growing curve
right
>> that doesn't mean it's going to continue
right we're testing thousand curves
we're working we're a thousand uh edit
deliveries right now doesn't mean it's
going to work but we're working on it
>> tripling year-over-year base edits
>> we don't know if it's going to work but
we are
>> but you think it might
>> it could early indicators have low
efficiency but it's working but there is
a point where large cargo swaps with DNA
synthesis is just better unfortunately
the people in that category don't really
have an a business driver to synthesize
DNA after a certain scale. Um, so we've
just started doing that internally.
>> So doing the math, tripling
year-over-year, you're at a thousand
base edits right now. That gives you
like four years.
>> We are consistently
north of 300. We're testing a,000. I
don't want I think it's highly likely we
will get that working.
>> What's the point at which it kind of
really goes crazy and you can do
whatever you want. Well, I I think the
synthesis is going to I think synthesis
will replace multiplex editing faster,
>> right? So, basically a machine that
generates the you know the the gigabase
code you want.
>> I think that's high I think that's has a
higher likelihood of success faster.
>> Okay.
>> So, Ben, you've come up with the
artificial egg.
>> Not the kind you eat, but the kind that
gives birth to a aven species. How far
are we from a lady here in the audience,
a young lady or older lady in the
audience having a baby in an artificial
womb?
a human.
>> Well, you have from a technology
perspective, I think it's a very
different answer than a societal and
acceptance and ethics and regul.
>> Okay. Okay. So, let's talk about an
artificial womb for mammal.
>> Yeah. Uh I I think within 24 months we
will colossal will birth animal mammals
um fully exudo
>> from gestation through delivery.
>> Yeah. That never went into a surrogate.
>> Wow.
>> That's pretty amazing.
>> Yeah. That's wild. [applause]
>> Hopefully hopefully sooner, but I I
think that 24 months is highly likely.
>> Wow. I I need I need to ask a quick
question.
>> Yeah.
>> Just a show of hands in the audience. Is
your mind blown?
>> Like, okay, just checking. Okay, got it.
>> Yeah.
>> Make sure I'm not alone here.
>> So, what's what's the iPhone moment in
in Colossal here? Or is it is it the
Willie Mammoth stepping onto the stage
or is there something else that I
>> I think that I [clears throat] think
it's I think
>> a WTF moment.
>> I think well I mean
>> I think we've had a little bit of those
already, but I think that I think the
next major inflection points are when we
show the world the next extinct species,
right? Like I think always at kind of in
that kind of zero to one week. When is
that? [laughter]
>> Just kidding.
>> Coming [clears throat] soon. Uh so so I
think I think that showing another
extinct species back um through
precision gene editing number one.
Number two I think that mamillian
artificial development and gestation is
number two. And then you know we are
working some on some things that we
haven't shared yet that I think are
equally as interesting to like
direwolves. So we have some more
surprise and delights. If if that
surprised you and delighted you, if that
surprised and scared, well then we have
that for you, too. So,
>> can I ask you about the data set
actually? So, so you know, protein
folding just really snuck up on
everybody. It's like solved overnight.
Been just a total gold mine of change
for all of biotech and
>> my daughter uses it every single day.
>> Yeah, we use I mean, yeah,
>> massive. So, the equivalent the genotype
to phenotype mapping problem where you
say, okay, this sequence produced that,
oh, that's Alex Wisner Gross. Okay, this
sequence. Oh, that produced the lane.
Great. This is Oh, that's a dodo bird.
[laughter] Okay,
>> I love this final jump there.
>> Just a couple.
>> We love that jump, by the [laughter]
way.
>> Um, so is there a point where given the
data set you're accumulating, you can
interpolate and you can say, "Okay, now
I don't have to create it. I know
exactly what would come out."
>> So, so we're doing it on a from a
product perspective, we're doing it on a
species basis currently, but we're
trying to extrapolate to large clades of
animals. So like sizing is a big one,
right? So if you go if you're taking
like our model species that we're
working with for the Tasmanian tiger uh
is orthotine is a fat tail done dunart
and it's a 1500x fold from a marsupial
mouse to a marupial wolf. Right? So
understanding that and and extrapolating
that and how that whether what what
regulates that not just the genes but
how and when it regulates in development
how does that transfer to like you know
can you make a killer whale the size of
you know your pet goldfish probably not
but you could probably scale within
certain levels of function. If you look
at certain uh species like dogs and also
certain certain species groups of birds,
they have tremendous scale functions,
right? Which are larger than 1500 um and
so so we're or 1500x. So, so we're
looking at it on a per from a um
non-trait engineering perspective but
from a purist perspective in uh
deextinction to look specifically at the
genes that drove X Y and Z but
separately we are then trying to
extrapolate that on a clay basis so that
we can say okay how can we affect sizing
even within some marginal you know 20
50% uh offshoot within other species so
I think that it's it's likely that like
coat code coat color sizing, um, you
know, placket like things that form
skin, scales,
feathers, all of that will be highly
measurable.
>> Um, and and be able to be inducible very
quickly.
>> Interesting. So, all right.
>> So, I don't know about everything, but
like, you know, we have a whole AI team
that's just working on uh patterning and
stripes. It's actually a really hard
problem.
>> Tusks, stripes, length of snout,
>> hair.
>> Hair. Yes. Hair. Yeah.
>> By the way, quite a bit.
>> You know, I when I took uh when Chris
and I took our boys down to Dallas to
visit, it was a real surprise and
delight to see the William ice there.
>> Yeah.
>> How many gene edits did that take?
>> Uh the first generation, which is what
we show the public uh was eight.
>> Yeah. Amazing.
>> In one delivery.
>> Eight base pairs.
>> Uh
>> eight edits.
>> Eight edits total in one. Eight base
edits in one delivery.
>> Got it.
>> Amazing. Let's go to some of the uh
audience questions here. from Bruno.
>> We may we may have a another version at
some point that more interesting.
>> I can't wait.
>> Yeah, that's interesting.
>> We'll have you back on Moonshots to talk
about it.
>> Great.
>> All right. So, Bruno asked, "Must a
moonshot tackle problem?"
>> We had we had Shatner there the other
day and I was like, "Fuck, if we
like
and tailless, we could have like gotten
like, you know, Shatner very excited
about Trible." So,
>> the tripbles. That's right. We need
tribles. You could bring triples back
>> just without
>> I think back is the wrong word, but I
think we could forward.
>> Bring them forward.
>> Bring it forward. [laughter]
>> All right. So, Bruno asked the following
of you. Uh, must a moonshot tackle one
enormous problem within a single
vertical or can it be horizontal
addressing a seemingly mundane everyday
uh need that cuts across many verticals?
And we'll ask that of Astro as well,
Captain Moonshot shortly.
>> Um, I think it can go ac like cross
verticals, right? But but remember I
have ADD and so like I think that the
that the the lack of focus gives us a
larger amount of wisdom across multiple
categories, right? And so we look at the
extinction as a systems problem, but
that same system modeling that can be
used to preserve species, bring back
species can also be used to do all kinds
of work specifically in human
healthcare. So, so I think that if if
you ground your fundamentals in what
you're trying to build, I think you can
apply it to many use cases and it
doesn't have to be so narrow that like
if you miss that window, it doesn't have
other broader applicability. Here's a
great question from Teresa. Uh, how are
you planning the ethical issues in
creating mammals exut? A mammal has
emotional needs and just creating an
animal doesn't relieve you of the
emotional burden of a living creature. I
think that's the same thing like if if
it's born ex utero do you give it a
family to live with it in a
>> so we do a lot I I think most people
don't know this because like you know
the media doesn't uh always cover all of
the stuff that we do we have a
foundation we open source all of our
technologies for uh conservation so
anybody can use any of our technologies
for conservation for free we have 75
global partners we're very grateful for
them but we've also funded projects
specifically around this right so like
ma uh mammoths and elephants are highly
social animals, right? So, we're not
going to bring back a mammoth. We're
bringing back herds of them. We have 16
different lines being worked on at the
same time.
>> How many?
>> We have 16 different lines working.
>> No. How how many total mammoths do you
want to bring back?
>> Do I want to bring back tens of
thousands?
>> Tens of thousands of mammoths.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow. In LA.
>> Um, they have to be Colombian mammoths
for here or Py.
>> I'm going to steal I'm gonna steal your
line. The mammoth in the room is where
do the mammoths go?
>> But going back going back to that Wait,
wait, wait, wait. Yeah, I want to answer
because it's I think it's a really
important, thoughtful question, right?
And so you've had you've had uh you know
California condors, you've had all these
different um uh close to extinct species
that that people work on and in and rear
in the rearing of it. And so we fund uh
in in while there's a halo effect of the
positivity of this for today for
elephants. It also has a broader
implication for what Colossal is trying
to do. We fund uh in Batswana an
incredible group called elephant havens
which is working with orphaned elephants
right that that have already been born
not actually but been born and been
abandoned for whatever reason and they
are working to use they use AI they use
a lot of different tools to figure out
how do we how do they create synthetic
herds from a very matriarchal society of
of elephants where they where elephants
where they don't currently get that how
do they rear those elephants and train
them to be elephants and also work
together in a herd right because because
that's how elephants behave. Separately,
we're funding and doing research in uh
everything from satellite imaging to
drones to AI, building programs in uh uh
different elephant migratory patterns in
corridors so that we can understand the
social dynamics and hierarchy of of
moving, right? And so that benefit all
of that technology in in that that data
uh impacts elephant conservation work
today, right? Right. So you don't you
don't have like elephant orphaned
elephants you have you can rew wild
entire herds but all that that data also
informs us how we are going to rear
these animals in a in a way where if
they are born exudo how do they grow up
in a social dynamic with the right
hierarchy
>> Dave you were going to say
>> so true story your guy George Church was
at a presentation that we had at MIT and
the topic was global warming and he said
well I have the you know the study I
have the cure for global warming we're
going to bring several but Yes, we're
going to bring back the woolly mammoth.
The woolly mammoth's native habitat is
Siberia and northern Canada.
>> The tundras.
>> The tundras. And back when they were
around, there were no trees because the
woolly mammoths
>> Yes.
>> walk around and knock down all the
trees.
>> And elephants actually do this in
Africa, too.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Force elephants. Yeah. Yeah.
They're incredible at this.
>> So, so we're like, well, what the hell
is the connection to global warming?
Because, well,
>> without the trees, the grass grows. The
grass actually sequesters more carbon
than the trees do. It's about six times
more efficient in a 2 to 3x albido
effect with light reflection to space.
>> Yeah. So I think I don't think you guys
checked in with the Canadians to see if
it's okay, but you turn them loose. Turn
them loose in Canada.
>> I don't live in the tundra.
>> I I'm from India actually.
>> Seriously though, where do we build?
>> So no, but this is a this is a a really
good point. So in the early days um and
I'm a big data guy so I most my
background is in software and a little
space hardware but for the most part I
just want to go where the data takes us
right
>> so you have high conviction really smart
scientists like George that will say if
you have this mammoth density at these
places uh in in the in the tundra
they'll have this impact on the uh
perafrost a lowering of six to eight
degrees in the summer months it only
melts so far so so you you can
extrapolate that out we have actually
done that exercise and it's quite
interesting then but it goes back down
to a top down versus a bottom up
approach of how they affect the
environment. There's other people in the
scientific community including at
Colossal that think that they will not
have that level of impact. Right? And so
um but the good news is is that
generally speaking whether they fall on
the what does how do you solve climate
change uh with mammoth uh at 10,000 plus
mammoth in the in the Arctic doesn't
really matter because they have a net
positive benefit on the environment in
terms of like helping restore that
ecosystem. So what I try to do and and
Palmer mentioned this in the last thing
is like how do you get two in a
room and get them to agree well it gets
extrapolated to like the 10th degree
when they're both PhDs and so [laughter]
uh which is like in my experience I
don't have a PhD and people think that I
have a war on academia at times but like
the pretty hard to deal with people out
there um or PhDs uh in my experience
they actually have a model where I have
found though is when you sit them down
and tell them that they're both right
and you help them walk through that it
actually works. And so what I've said is
maybe George is right that this level of
density of mammoths at this at this lat
long at latitude longitude will have
this level of impact. But maybe others
are right saying that it will have a
positive benefit on the flora and fauna,
but it won't cure carbon uh climate
trees. Either way, it doesn't really
matter if it's having a net positive
benefit on uh elephants today as well as
uh the ecosystem that of the tundra
which is highly degraded. So, everyone
can agree that the the ecosystem sucks
and we need to make it better, right?
And so, so I I've done that and you
know, I don't know. I I don't want to
say that George is right, but I'll just
say I've looked at the math
>> and I think George is pretty smart.
>> Okay,
>> Ben, you just spun out Astromec,
multi-billion dollar company from the
start. What is Astromemech doing?
>> So, we're looking at So, so this was
kind of a tea up from your question. um
the uh foundation models and ad models
aren't quite looking at the entire tree
of life and they're not like uh they're
not going to magically overnight give
them a genome and give us an answer. So
we are trying to build like what are
kind of infle we we call them internally
inflection models. What are deflection
models that can plug into those
foundational models that can say okay
we've studied and we understand
everything about this genome sequence
across how it's uh evolved and more
importantly when it evolved and why it
didn't evolve in related clades and then
we're looking at everything from like
climate like like what what spurred that
because we want to build essentially a
prediction model to say okay where did
that go and why did it go because I
don't think that astromeme's going to
have the like magic you know anthropic
mythos those, you know, $4 trillion or
whatever the latest round is that that
that solves all things all ways. But
what I do think is I think it'll have
enough of the unique data sets in how to
classify and understand that data data
set that it can plug into those so that
when you do have global bio volts and
you have millions of samples that you
can feed into a mythos, this can be
acting like kind of the um or a mythos
like competitor that this can be acting
as like your traffic control cop of
where to go and where to focus.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Let me synthesize a couple of
questions here. What's the biggest
problem you wish people were working on?
The biggest moonshot that people are not
right now.
>> I think I think that the we are going to
lose half of biodiversity in the next 25
years. And everyone who loves us and
hates us agrees with that. So we need to
do something about it. Governments like
this is not going to be solved by a zoo
or a nonprofit. We have to have billions
of dollars of federal funding. across
multiple governments working together to
at least back up life. We back up
everything else. We back up our, you
know, we back up our photos, we back up
our texts, our emails, we back up
everything. But ultimately, I think most
people back up their text and emails,
but so some people use Signal. But like
for the most part [laughter] though, um
I I I really think that we we have got
to right now uh invest in infrastructure
to back those species up because if you
don't like when we lose those species,
we're going to have negative impacts on
ecosystems. When we lose those species,
we're going to have negative impacts in
the food web for the animals. But so if
you like ecosystems, you should back it
up. If you don't like ecosystems and you
hate the environment, but you like
animals, you should back it back up. You
hate the environment and animals, but
you like humans. You should back
it up. You know, there's data in there
that will help humanity.
>> Just as a quick aside, you know, one of
my companies uh with an amazing CEO, Bob
Hurer, called Cellularity, we have
something called LifeBank USA that when
your baby is born, you store all the
placental cells. Yep.
>> And you've got basically the original
boot desk. You've got your kids stem
cells, te- cells, natural killer cells,
everything. And it's like if your baby
came with an extra set of organs, would
you throw them away? Probably not. But
why throw away, you know, the placenta
is the 3D printer that creates the
creates the baby. So, I mean, this kind
of envisioning
>> of of of safety of backups is amazing.
So, this is what this is what you're
doing right now in Dubai.
>> We're doing in Dubai. We're we just
announced a partnership with uh US Fish
and Wildlife here as part of Secretary
Interior's directive on backing up the
natural resources that that that make
America great. So, we're doing that now
here domestically. Uh we have two other
governments we haven't announced yet uh
that we'll announce when they want to
announce that are part of our framework.
Um and then it's also kind of like what
George and I also talk about with open
source. It's completely open. So we any
nonprofit, any academic institution, any
big foundation, any private individuals
to anybody in Palmer secret billionaire
boys club that wants to throw money
wants boys. Are you in the B boys group?
>> So So the anybody [laughter] that like
I'm not I'm not in any secret Jack
groups.
>> I have a quick question.
>> All right, let's close it out with your
quick question. I want to be Ben Lamb
with the mind as creative and crazy as
yours to envision these things.
>> How do I go about doing that?
>> Oh, how you do what?
>> How do I go about
>> how did you become
>> how do I become take on the mindsets
that you have to apply technology as
incredibly creatively as you have done?
>> So I uh well it's very kind. I think
that uh I I'm very curious, right? So, I
I like to just learn new things. And I
think in a world, especially with AI,
where everyone's got every answer to
their um at their tool at their
fingertips, I'm pretty good at telling
people what I don't know. So, I think I
kind of take a childlike wonder to
things and just say, "Hey, I don't know
this, but I'm sure I could uh go find
the answer." And what I've also found,
which most people, this is big advice
that I'd also give everyone, people will
help you. Like, I am an optimist. I
believe in technology, but I believe in
humanity first. And people will help
you. So like I don't think people ask
enough
on subways and looking at their
phones, but if you just look out for a
second and ask for help, people will
help you. And so it's like when I don't
understand something, sometimes I will
call people in this in like some of our
top adviserss at Colossal are adviserss
cuz I just cold email them like, "Hey, I
don't understand this. My teams are
telling me this. You're the world's
expert of this. Can you have a meeting
with me?" They have no this this woman
or man has no reason to talk to me,
right? But they'll take the call. And so
I feel like I just have this general
curiosity wrapped with
>> people like you. They want to help.
>> No, I think that they'll like everybody
like I really do. I think you can just
if people ask for help, nine out of 10
times I believe in humanity, they will
help you. Ask
>> a quick give it up for that. Right.
>> [applause]
>> uh a curiosity mindset, a purpose-
driven mindset, and a quick question
from Kathy Wood backstage who said,
"Yesterday, Anthropic um uh you know set
up their announced their wet labs to uh
that were able to create something like
crisper-like. Does this light a fire in
your work or does it you know, kill
forward momentum?"
>> So, I think it's massively validating,
right? Like um it's a great question.
Kathy's great. I think it's really
important, right? Like there are so many
problems to solve in biology. The these
technologies are we are just like we
haven't even opened the door like the
doors barely cracked barely barely
cracked open. I think that what they
announced yesterday like people see that
and say oh my gosh biotech is going to
be dead because it should be anthropic
in their in their lives. That's not true
right that that's just not true. And so
I think that that was a huge watershed
moment for the industry to show that
like you have the AI companies that
understand and yes background in biology
but but you have the AI companies that
that understand that that will be one of
the most accepted use cases and
deployments of their technology and that
people want to have healthier families
healthier longer lives right so it was a
great thing for the society
>> really sure do you have a pd doom or do
you need to even think about the
question
>> you I'm an optimist
Like I I am an optimist. Like I don't
agree with, you know, I I think we're
going to have some scary moments and I
think that's okay, right? Because I do
believe in human ingenuity to work
through those problems, right? But I
think that you've got to have a
conversation. I do think that the media
is overselling that a little bit right
now. um to to to be kind. But I do think
that like you know we we really will get
there and you we're going to have a
couple scary moments, but it's like you
have turbulence on planes and everyone
still lands, right? Like that's okay.
>> All right, welcome to the Oscars of
Optimism. Give it up for Ben Lamb.
[music]